Guide to the California Rural Legal Assistance, Inc. records M0750
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
- Record Group 8. Government Relations, circa 1966-2000
  - Series 1. Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and Legal Services Corporation (LSC)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes correspondence, press clippings, reports, questionnaires related to monitoring CRLA, Texas Rural Legal Aid (TRLA), other organizations (19 folders), circa 1981-1986 (Carton 6)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; include preparation and planning materials, statistics, notes and memos; CRLA responses and final report; also includes IOLTA review materials (23 folders), circa 1983-1988 (Carton 8)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes reports, audits, document requests, correspondence, financial summaries, migrant unit issues, regional information, notes, miscellaneous (34 folders), circa 1983-1988 (Carton 9)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes memos, correspondence, financial records, and other material related to the 1985 LSC monitoring visit and CRLA's reaction to the report that followed (36 folders) (Carton 112)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes memos, correspondence, financial records, and other material related to the 1985 LSC monitoring visit and CRLA's reaction to the report that followed (14 folders) (Carton 113)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes memos, notes, correspondence, and other material related to the CRLA and CRLA Foundation requested by the 1985 LSC monitors; also news clippings concerning the 1985 monitoring (28 folders) (Carton 142)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes documents requested by LSC monitors as well as summaries of monitors' visits to CRLA offices (20 folders), 1985 (Carton 235)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes financial statements, Board minutes, and other materials requested by the 1985 LSC monitors (20 folders) (Carton 144)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes memos, financial records, and correspondence requested by the 1985 LSC monitors (17 folders), 1986 (Carton 119)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes minutes, articles, conference proceedings, operations manual, docket notebook, timesheets, and other material requested by the 1985 LSC monitors (12 folders), 1986 (Carton 120)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC) monitoring; includes description, analysis, clarrification, memos, and correspondence relating to LSC regulations; LSC monitoring audit files including procedures, instructions, forms, office visit and staff listing, monitoring team assignments, memorandums and correspondence relating to audits (43 folders), 1981-1986 (Carton 221, Folders 43)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC), Board meeting agendas (24 folders), 1984-1987 (Carton 236)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC); "Next Step" conference and reports (6 folders), 1978-1980 (Box 55)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC), Private Bar Involvement; includes memos, correspondence, reports, news clippings, newsletters, and training materials related to the LSC's Private Bar Involvement mandate (15 folders), 1982-1985 (Carton 73)
    - Legal Services Corporation (LSC), statistics (11 folders), 1980-1985 (Box 206)
  - Series 2. Reagan Veto
    - Reagan veto: includes OEO grant application materials (1969), CRLA’s legal counsel contract, Carlucci commission reports and memos, miscellaneous historical files related to the Reagan veto; drafts and copies of article by Jerome B. Falk and Stuart R. Pollak, "Political Interference with Publicly Funded Lawyers: The CRLA Controversy and the Future of Legal Services" (10 folders), circa 1969-1973 (Box 45)
    - Reagan veto; includes correspondence, news clippings, memoranda, and reports related to CRLA's fight against Reagan's attempt to veto funding for the CRLA; includes a copy of the Uhler Report (32 folders), 1970-1971 (Carton 78)
    - Reagan veto; includes CRLA’s response to the Uhler Report, reports and contracts related to OEO commission; news clippings, press releases, correspondence, articles; Uhler questionnaire (63 folders), circa 1970-1971 (Carton 29)
    - Reagan veto; includes correspondence, budgets, reports, memoranda and other documents related to CRLA's fight against Reagan's attempt to veto funding for the CRLA (25 folders), 1970-1971 (Carton 75)
    - Reagan veto; includes memos, correspondence, press releases, news clippings, and mailing lists relating to CRLA’s campaign to overturn Reagan’s veto of CRLA funding (25 folders), 1970-1971 (Carton 66)
    - Reagan veto; includes news clippings, memos, and reports relating to CRLA’s campaign to overturn Reagan’s veto of CRLA funding (4 folders), 1969-1971 (Box 67)
    - Reagan veto; includes news clippings and editorials related to Reagan's veto of funding for CRLA (9 folders), 1971 (Box 159)
    - Reagan veto; includes news clippings and magazine articles related to Reagan's veto of funding for CRLA (18 folders), 1970-1971 (Carton 173)
    - Reagan veto; includes news clippings, reports, a support letters index, and other material related to Reagan's veto of funding for CRLA (8 folders), 1971-1972 (Box 174)
  - Series 3. Miscellaneous Government Relations
    - Madera letter; includes correspondence, notes, memos, and news clippings related to accusations made by the Board of Supervisors in Madera County that CRLA pursued cases to increase their own publicity and stir up controversy (15 folders), 1981 (Box 114)
    - Madera letter; includes exhibits gathered by CRLA in response to complaints lodged by the city of Madera (5 folders), 1980-1983 (Carton 204, Folders 18-22)
    - Private law firms and pro-bono activities; includes memos, correspondence, and budgets related to CRLA's coordination of activities with private law firms concerning pro bono legal activity (3 folders), 1982-1985 (Box 205, Folders 1-3)
    - Relations with local organizations and government; includes correspondence and memos on CRLA involvement with CETA and the City of San Francisco's Community Services Administration, 1977-78, 1981 (Carton 268, Folders 1-2)
    - Relations with national organizations and government; includes correspondence and memoranda on CRLA involvements with the Coalition of Legal Services, congressional inquiries in Gilroy, Modesto, and Hollister, Gramm-Rudman Legislation, Congressmen Leon Panetta and Robert Kastenmeier, Legal Services Corporation, the Reagan veto, the San Diego Project, and Save Legal Services, 1966-1971, 1975, 1977, 1981-83, 1985-89 (Carton 268, Folders 9-32)
    - Relations with state and national organizations; includes correspondence, memos, and other materials on CLRA involvements with the National Economic and Law Center, the California Department of Health, the California Rural Health Policy Council, and other organizations (7 folders), 1995-2000 (Box 289)
    - Relations with state organizations and government; includes correspondence and memos on CRLA involvement with the California Fair Political Practices Commission, Californians of Asian Ancestry, National Clients Council Region VIII, and the Western Center on Law and Poverty, 1977-1984 (Carton 268, Folders 3-8)
    - State Bar of California Trust Fund/IOLTA applications; includes notes, memos, correspondence, and application materials for IOLTA funds from the State Bar of California (11 folders), 1984-1988 (Carton 74)
    - U.S. Congress; includes correspondence, memos, and other materials related to CRLA's interactions with members of the United States Congress, especially Leon Panetta, concerning allegations of the CRLA's misuse of funds (6 folders), 1988-1990 (Box 205, Folders 4-9)
- Record Group 9. Born-Digital material, circa 1982-1993; 6.0 computer file(s) (PDF) (4 - 5.25" floppy disks in 1 half-box)
  Access
  Files on disks in folders 1 and 2 are unreadable and are not available. Files on disks in folders 3 and 4 have been printed out and are available as hard copies in the folders.
  This series consists of documents created and/or stored on 5.25" floppy disks by CRLA.
  The majority of material in this record group was removed from other record groups. Separated material notes, which describe the original location of the item, have been added when relevant.
  - SM-Config files (5.25" floppy disk), Abascal papers (Half-box 371, Folder 1)
    Removed from Record Group 2, Box 168
  - General Services Report (5.25" floppy disk) (Half-box 371, Folder 2)
    Removed from Record Group 4, Carton 137, folder 37, General Services Foundation Migrant Parents
  - Mixed files; includes Cotello v. Vouziers (Complaint for Damages) Valerie Small Navarro memos, CRLAF SLIAG report; (5.25" in floppy disk), 1991 (Half-box 371, Folder 3)
    Removed from Record Group 5, Steven Rosenbaum TPS/ABC Settlement SAW issues immigration
  - Zambrano V. INS, press release; (5.25" floppy disk), 1989 (Half-box 371, Folder 4)
    Removed from Record Group 5, Carton 228 Zambrano v. INS